wow Blast from the Past okay
uh hi we just got back from a tour uh we
went to first we went to
Japan and uh it was wonderful and uh we
were invited by a company uh that works
there
and I don't know it was kind of a
strange thing they had me up on the
stage with all these uh famous Japanese
what do you call it motivational
speakers one guy sold 20 million books
every third family has his book in Japan
and uh it was really nice and then we
spent time with a very famous
Diamond dealer who's the largest private
jewelry collection in the world from
starting from 3,000 years ago
Mesopotamia and uh that was really
awesome and Orit put on Queen
Elizabeth's diamond 10000 million
diamond necklace and but he wouldn't let
her go home with it and uh then we went
to Shenzhen South
China and uh we're doing a special
program there uh called
actionpie and um then we went to Vienna
and uh we had a wonderful time there and
there's a I think that's the sixth year
they're on the sixth year of DCI program
so they're halfway through and uh
they're just amazing it's called D what
do you call
deut a and all the German speaking uh
countries so they all come there and we
have a good time and it was just amazing
but we went around the world in 10 days
or something it was kind of hard
physically uh but uh the thing in China
was interesting because um I was using
this teaching which is called angel
devil right uh danging Shang in in
tibetan it's called dangen Shang it's
about a 300 years old teaching and uh
it's given by the first Pion llama uh
who was a
famous poet uh great great philosopher
one of the best in history and a
pacifist a great pacifist who personally
prevented a war uh in Tibet and so it's
it's a cool book come in handsome sit
down
Mark just kidding
uh and uh so I you know I'm supposed to
come up with 12 DCI levels and uh DCI is
a business training organization and we
use the ancient
wisdom uh to teach business people
around the world so the uh team in China
this trip uh has 2 million followers
it's a it's a community of 2 million
business people and uh so we talked to
the 40 top people and that was amazing
and I was trying to get a new uh idea
for them you know I like your ha uh and
uh and then I was thinking this would be
a really nice class uh to use there
because uh what this book is about and
it's very famous and it hasn't
really there hasn't been a good
translation uh and I think we should do
one uh it needs a commentary the PO it's
poetry and it's too uh it's too
difficult to understand without some
kind of commentary so when I have a free
day I'll I'll write a commentary uh and
it's it's going to be nice I think it's
a spiritual classic I think it'll be
like uh I don't know Dante's Inferno or
something and uh it's an amazing amazing
book but it's basically an argument in
one person's mind uh between
understanding and
understanding so it's a very famous uh
dangen means a tendency to see things
that aren't there Shang means uh like a
what do you call it like a fierce
argument where they're tearing each
other apart and uh it's in one person's
mind okay so the whole uh argument it's
an argument within one person's mind and
it's a it's amazing uh and then it's
when he introduces it he calls it uh
this is a book on mahamudra okay what's
the main emphasis of a mahamudra book
your own mind yeah you're meditating on
your own mind and it's supposed to be
better do you remember why anybody not
the human computer huh it's always there
it's always there you don't have to buy
a meditation
object the yeah it's the most
interesting thing to people and it's
constantly changing so it's interesting
to watch so the those of you who are
like me and Bang Your Head on the closet
when you fall asleep during
meditation uh it's supposed to be uh
particularly effective meditation to use
your own mind as the object of
meditation okay and he starts out with
that he starts out with describing why
it's a mahamudra meditation okay
mahamudra also refers to experiences you
have as you die okay so as you die then
uh parts of your body open up and you
get uh flashes of insight by Nature not
by training okay so uh it also refers to
the direct perception of of certain
deeper truths uh while you're in the act
of dying okay so that's all called path
path mahamudra okay sorry uh she
Foundation mahamudra okay and then uh so
what we've been using this text do and
and it's a thing we call diamond mining
which Nick can tell you about tomorrow
maybe so upstairs here we have a we have
a whole department uh ancient book
translation department and I'm going to
tell you about it tomorrow I have a
presentation tomorrow about it but uh
basically we are translating the ancient
Classics of Buddhism a 2 and a half
thousand years of uh Classics and uh
she's just amazed about it and uh it's
okay and uh we think of it has snow on
the mountain on the top of the mountain
so in our College the snow falls
upstairs and people sit up there and
they they we go through the ancient
Classics of Buddhism and they're
extremely difficult and uh and we're
going through them in in an amazing way
I'll tell you more about it tomorrow but
then uh we see it as the snow melts and
the water comes
downstairs and then down here we we
teach teachers uh mainly right now
Diamond Cutter Institute teachers which
is business programs uh but we base them
on the ancient
wisdom so we have a constant flow of new
snow upstairs and we have constant flow
of new ideas coming downstairs and
my I have two reasons to give these
talks in Sedona I mean one is uh some of
the people who work here in the college
you know have moved here from all over
the world and um we don't see each other
very
often uh to be honest I think I'm here
half the year and when I'm here I'm
sleeping off the jet leg and doing
gardening and trying to see my partner
and uh Veronica and thanks for your nice
note and uh you know so I have to it's a
what do you call delicate line to to
walk like not being home enough and when
I'm home I have to be home so uh then we
just end up not seeing each other very
much so I thought uh it would be nice uh
I I would like to give these talks three
or four times a year and um I think it's
nice that we just all see each other and
uh people often move to
Sedona thinking that they're going to
see us and and then they move away 6
months later having never seen anyone
and uh you know we're just all really
really busy doing sweet things although
is falling asleep right now he's
building a yoga
studio and doing other things and
running the whole translation department
so anyway the idea is we take the
ancient wisdom we go diamond mining we
pick out great ideas and then we Tred to
use it in real life and I think last
year 30,000 people came to uh deci
programs we have a talk in uh Taipei in
two weeks I think uh 3,000 people are
signed
up uh but I think if we do it here two
things happen I think our community gets
a little closer to each other we see
each
other you know it's an excuse to see
each other and I think uh secondly it
helps me to have a little uh
laboratory uh where I can test out new
ideas if you fall asleep right away then
I'll change I'll change the presentation
slightly and uh and like that and it's
been working we had some nice uh
experiences in China we taught this we
taught what I taught you last what was
it December
November uh I taught it in China for two
days and it it was really cool we had a
really really good time and uh so I
think it's my idea is to go on like that
so how do you use this text in your real
life
uh we all have an internal conversation
you know and we have a
we've we've promised 12 DCI levels we're
on level we just finished level 10 right
which is about managing anger uh and
then
uh people keep asking me what's level 11
we we released the new level every
November in
Berlin cuz Germany's where we started uh
the first level the first time the first
level started kind of in Austria right
Peter where are
you
yeah you you were the first organizer I
think ever he organized something in
Vienna and then uh a volcano blew up in
uh
Iceland and there were no international
flights uh and I was stuck in New York
and and he had paid $88,000 for the
prince's
Palace and
uh I couldn't go and that's so that was
the first DCI event ever we finally got
on the first flight out and the
president of Lu tza was on the plane cuz
he swore it wouldn't fall down and he
was willing to fly with us you know so
we were like okay then they flew to
Africa and up and uh anyway uh so every
year the first level is held in the new
level is revealed in Germany and I'm
working on it and it's called the inner
conversation and it's based on this text
okay like how to monitor your inner
conversation I thought it was so
original and cool and then people showed
me like 12 business books already called
inner conversations
so so that's okay
uh and the idea is that there's a good
part of your mind and a bad part of your
mind okay and and we have that little
picture in America of the devil and
talking to the Angel and the devil says
you know I don't know eat more chocolate
and the angel says that's not good for
you and they then they argue in your
mind right
and uh so this whole text written uh I
don't know 400 years ago it's a it's a
real angel versus devil talk okay but
it's different it's a lot different and
they're talking about a battle between
two states of mind okay and most people
don't have this battle because it's the
understanding of
emptiness fighting uh the Mind who
doesn't understand emptiness who
understands it
partially okay like a partial
understanding so he's picking on uh
people who have a partial understanding
of emptiness slightly
wrong and then uh against that devil is
the Angel and the the angel is a perfect
understanding of
emptiness and the goal is according to
this
idea that if you understand
emptiness uh you would never have
problems in your life uh especially with
people okay and I I use this uh in
conversation I used to text myself I try
to try it on myself cuz I need it every
day cuz I meet irritating people every
day okay like word and uh just kidding
not uh but you know I do you know we're
so busy and we meet so many people and
we we work in so many countries and
we're tired because we just got off the
plane and we had two hours of sleep or
something and uh and so I do have
personal challenges I do meet people who
give me a hard time and then uh if you
understand emptiness if you have a
strong angel in your mind uh you can
turn it into a beautiful thing you see
you can uh not just not get angry but
you can actually turn it into a almost
Divine experience when you meet
irritating people so that would be a
nice thing to learn right so that
basically that's what we're going to do
for three days uh how to use an
understanding
emptiness uh
to when you have challenges uh basically
okay you can use it for goals of course
but I think uh each of us the first
motivation in life is to avoid suffering
uh irritating people and uh I think
let's talk about it in that context okay
challenges with your health or financial
challenges or personal problems uh how
do how do you use the inner conversation
to deal with that okay and uh we're uh
pretty deep into the text I've been
teaching this text for six or seven
years often on more often on and uh my
goal is to finish it I I think I can
finish by
2022 and uh if we go kind of at this
rate and uh so I think uh we're kind of
halfway through and I beg the uh
patience of people who haven't come
before because if I review the whole
thing as as I did last last time and the
time before and the time before and the
time before we won't get we'll never
finish okay so if you haven't been to
this series in the last six seven years
just relax okay you can use the angel on
me as the irritating person in your life
tonight and uh I'll teach you how to do
okay so don't get all excited and don't
give up and it's you know he was a great
philosopher uh he's going very deep he's
going very subtle and I just want to
jump into that I don't want to review
again the whole thing which we did last
time okay uh now tools I gave you some
tools okay you're going to have a
reading every
night uh which is about 25 more verses
from his poem
and uh we will never cover them but at
least you have it in your hand and then
there's my notes uh to the verses
because I don't
think without an explanation I don't
think you can see where it's going okay
so I'm going to teach from the
notes and I'm not going to do this gy
Michael thing of explain every single
Tibetan word because I I learned that
over the course of the last 5 six years
it's too much for people and it goes too
slow so I'm going just kind of kind of
I'm going to follow the flow of ideas
I'll tell you what verse we're on then
you go home and try to fit the verse to
what I said okay and and I think that's
the only way we'll ever get done with
this text okay he lived to 100 for me to
finish this I'm going to have to do the
same so uh I'm just saying well he said
he lived 100 which in Old you're talking
about country where people died at 40
and he was very unusual he he lived in '
92 or something like that but he's
called the 100e llama and uh okay so
here we go uh he what is the state of
mind that can protect you and when you
meet an irritating person or you have a
problem in your life the the landlord of
your new yoga studio it's a pain in the
ass and uh like how can you use this uh
internal conversation uh to deal with
that problem okay and I do mean uh
internal conversation okay and this is a
kind of meditation all right it's a
meditation that you walk around with all
day long and and as your mind talks to
your mind which it does right all the
time you train uh an angel to step in
and pick up the conversation you see and
how often do you need to use it uh about
once every five minutes okay and I'm not
kidding you know I have a normal we all
have our own work we have our own life
we meet at people Rosa is a famous
fashion designer and uh you meet people
all day and you have challenges all day
we all have we equally have challenges
so
uh you can learn to use this angel in
your head okay and and he would say one
more thing when he advertises he he
would say if you get it if you manage to
install the angel in your mind where she
can talk every five minutes okay you
will be a happy person for the rest of
your life and you will be super
successful and if you don't you cannot
be happy so he's he's not saying uh
you'll be
happier he's not saying that he's saying
if you don't understand where the world
is coming from you will never really be
happy okay
things will conspire to make you unhappy
okay uh every time you're unhappy you
are misunderstanding the world okay and
and so he's very radical he's he's
saying I don't want to improve your life
you know either you get an angel in your
head or you don't if you do your life is
perfect and if you don't your life sucks
and there's no in between he does not
propose an in between okay so here we go
so actually we're going
after Angels who aren't
quite great okay nice but not no cigar I
was trying to explain this to a Chinese
friend nice but no cigar he's like
what's cigar got to do with it what does
cigar have to do I don't know but anyway
WC Fields not quite perfect okay so he's
going after meditations which are not
quite perfect okay which is good for
people like most of you who have been
trying to meditate for 20 years or 25
years and you know he's pointing out
subtle flaws in meditation okay for us
okay so I think it's a good it's a good
uh text for the people in this room I'd
say the average meditation re in this
room is about 20 that I'm aware of 25 50
okay
just
kidding okay I'm on verse uh I'm going
to start at 117 which is where we left
off last time and um don't worry too
much about looking at it okay I would
encourage you to just listen and take
the text home and and look at it at home
okay uh first look at the notes then
you'll remember what I said and then
look at the poetry and see how it
matches the notes okay see if you can
figure that out so that's your homework
okay and you can do it for the next few
weeks or it doesn't matter take it home
and you know like before you go to bed
or something just chew on it in a little
bit okay all right here we go so in
verse 117 he's talking about a special
meditation in the structure of this book
I wouldn't put it there take it down
yeah I don't no they're going to look at
that and not listen Okay read it at home
figure out at home what I said okay but
uh he's talking
about there's a huge section where he's
going to talk
about ideas of meditation that were
popular in Tibet 400 years ago okay
there were Tibet was uh what do you call
exploding with this new Buddhism stuff
and people were coming up with all kinds
of meditations you know and so he the
first part of his book is pointing out
how uh they're not quite they're nice
but they're not they no cigar nice but
no
cigar close but no cigar okay so there
he says you know that's nice that's good
that you're meditating but you know you
could do better uh so he's kind of
nitpicking people in his own culture and
in his culture Buddhism exploded it was
like every corner had a yoga studio and
there was a yoga teacher in every yoga
studio who made up a meditation that
they thought would be cool and and then
he's critiquing them okay uh he goes
through that uh it's I think it's
26 uh critiques of different kinds of
meditation and then he Nick Nick will be
interested he then he turns to the
classic schools of meditation he turns
to 2,000 years of Buddhist meditations
and he takes those uh starting with the
schools that were popular in India
before the Buddha okay so he kind of
does the Ben Kramer's sedon text where
he starts with the ancient schools of
India before the Buddha came he talks
about what they think meditation is and
then he starts in on the Buddhist
schools and he works his way up from the
lower schools and I was wondering you
know and I thought to POS it to
you uh and I've been doing this in China
I'll say $500 for the best answer I I
sometimes I lose like3 $4,000 every
night and uh Veronica told me to'd be
Tacky in the United
States
right
should he won 3,000 one day uh now I'm
not going to do that you guys are
motivated uh but uh but I'll ask you a
question I'm curious maybe Hector's a
Hector's into this kind of question
question I think uh why does he do it
this way I mean if he's going to talk
about Maham mudra like how to do a
proper meditation on The Emptiness of
your
mind uh
why why devote most of his book to
faulty systems you know pick nitpicking
uh the local yoga teachers meditation
system like why and then he nitpicks all
the great uh thinkers of Buddhism
one by one who's not the Gina you know
so what do you think why why does he do
it why did he write a book in a negative
way that's a I'm just curious what you
think bunny maybe because that's what
your mind would do abs is going through
yeah I think that's one good answer I
think uh and and they say all four all
the great schools of Buddhism were
taught by the
Buddha uh because he was anticipating uh
mistakes that we would make so you can
say
this book is not historical this book is
metaphorical and it's a it's a review of
all the mistakes that a normal person
will make in their meditation and kind
of by blaming it on some other school he
makes us feel better about ourselves you
know you know you in private you're like
oh that I was doing that yesterday I was
doing that meditation yesterday I
thought it was really good and then
you're like oh yeah that school is not
very good you know and uh anybody
else why is it I mean it's kind of
disturbing that it's negative Peter
Pik is
it
Mas okay
go we have never
experienced it's extremely difficult to
get there so we must have the tendency
to be half happy with something which is
not whole thing and then you give up
stay and you don't go to the end okay
good yeah so we we want to get it and we
try and then what we do isn't
cigar and then uh we get discouraged and
quit something like that okay anybody
else I mean why the negative
approach okay um if we're going to
succeed we have to catch our own mind
in all the many different
ways so that's basically it's it's
pointing out all
those
yeah I'll talk about that for a second
and I'll come back to you okay well
that's the practice of Buddhism is to
find our mind where it is staken uhhuh
and and apply
the the whole thing that's the whole
approach Nick and the more subtle our
misunderstanding gets the more we think
we're right more
yeah somebody over here Alex process of
elimination nice I like that
yeah yeah I think I think so far what
I've read I've only read like three qus
ofbody it's about 50 different wrong
meditations so yeah how many can we do I
don't know Michael doctor you don't know
what it is you can't be yeah good yeah
it's a Buddhist principle that to uh
defeat a negativity you have to know
what it looks like yeah and by the way
he's going to have a beautiful verse
about
that diamond mining when you never saw a
diamond
Lisa difficult to speak the truth so say
what it's not
n yeah cool okay yeah go out it that way
also be a really short book if he just
talked
about Hector
idea I think it's speeding our progress
instead of taking eons to get those
understandings it's saying look at the
vast ocean of human thought about what
reality is inside and outly your mind
and so investigate this way uh
investigate this one uh and and then you
go but this is Buddhism this one has
those four seals is is look we're all
Buddhist and then it moves you up there
and up there and so it's the answer that
everyone day really it's like pushing us
to the edges the misunderstanding the
duure but it's speeding up if I had to
do that on my own it would take me
lifetimes beyond measure yeah all the of
cool I haven't read the last quarter
like I don't know if he keeps being
negative or I don't know what happens at
the end word I didn't offer any money
but you can answer anyway by
uh well I have simple answerers he's a
gal answer debate
text yeah he's uh he's of the Buddhist
School of Tibet which which
especially appreciated the ancient
tradition of of uh debate give the wrong
answer like seven yeah and that's a
principle in debate like uh when you
start a debate you always say something
slightly wrong slightly wrong and then
you let the other guy try to prove you
wrong especially if you're a senior monk
trying to train a junior monk instead of
saying this is what's correct this is
what correct you you say is this correct
and you give them a slightly wrong idea
and they know it's supposed to be
slightly wrong and they have to beat you
you know uh they have to find what's
slightly wrong and that's how that's how
Buddhist education goes what's it called
the three
steps a Buddhist pedagogy ped pedagogy
super yeah super the last sorry yeah oh
Shen Shena raka R
Shaka okay shapa means Nick wake up are
you go man you got to take some drugs
before you come
here yeah so in the classic uh Buddhist
method of Education you don't write a
textbook you write a book of wrong ideas
and the student studies that first Shena
and then presentation of our position
then you present the correct position
then word what do you do then you let
the other guy who's really us yeah come
back not really yeah then you let the
other guy come back and and then you
destroy him again yeah he gets to
Counterattack you see so uh and then by
listening to all the wrong ideas you
learn something okay which is how life
goes right you screw up and then you I
wrote a book with a a Russian friend
right is Becky friend he's uh
karimov and he has sold 30 million books
which is like I haven't sold 1 million
books
and and uh so he he came to one of my
lectures and in Europe and and we
decided to write a book together uh
because of the anti-muslim stuff going
on in this in this country so I thought
it'd be cool to write a book with a
Muslim author uh Maria helped us a
lot and uh
we did we made a PCT that we would write
a book called the 10 biggest
mistakes in life and how to how not to
make them or something like that cuz
he's the same age as me and he's a
rascal we have a DCI joke I don't know
why I have to meet these people uh and
uh so then we both rode for 6 months and
then he called me back he got back to me
I forget if you sent me this email but
um he said look uh five mistakes my life
ain't going to make it I got like a
hundred you know can we change the name
of the book you know
so the book is still called 10 biggest
mistakes in your life but the first half
is his mistakes and then you turn the
book over and then there's my 10 so we
got 20 but we still kept the book
title makes
sense okay anyway I started reading his
finally it's good uh so yeah if you
start from mistakes it's better I think
okay ready for some s okay this is bad
meditation number 12 I didn't want to
call them bad because it's bad to call
people bad so I called it ineffective
meditation number 12 okay and that's he
proposes okay this other guy proposes
sit down close your eyes and watch
thoughts pop up pop up on your mind okay
and that will take you to happiness you
know that's that's a way that you can
deal
with uh unpleasant people okay is there
any
I'm going to ask you two questions okay
number one is there any benefit you can
see to that
approach and two is it ultimate does it
fix the problem number one is there
anything good about that approach sure
what training your mind to watch the
thoughts that are yeah yeah cool better
yeah and well don't forget what we're
talking about is is a state of mind that
you hold all day the inner conversation
it's a monitor
somebody for no I can't say
that there's two important Tools in all
meditation practices tra and
Sh okay T and Sh and alarm yeah but
which one comes
first yeah sh which is a a smoke alarm
okay it's a smoke alarm and it it's a
state of mind that you train in your
meditation mind to go off beep beep beep
if you start thinking about something
else right what are the two class
things you other things you start
thinking
about food
and food and sex yeah
uh yeah it's uh what do we call it Ching
right what's Ching
chin yeah like your buying is too busy
which means I like to say you're
thinking about lunch okay and then cha
you're sleepy yeah you get sleepy which
is the result of lunch if you try to eat
before meditating okay so these are the
two classic uh faults of meditation
somebody tell me what's a
STI equal staying in between those two
FS yeah it's the Sanskrit word one of
the many Sanskrit words for meditation
is samapti which means a state of
balance which means you are watching not
getting sleepy and you're watching not
getting too high and it's compared to
driving a car driving a car yeah like if
you watch a good drive ever their hands
are moving constantly and a person who's
a good meditator they're they're
constantly correcting themselves as they
go okay between those
two now that's not what we're but yeah
so the positive part of this meditation
number
12 other guys meditation the the good
part is that you would become sensitive
to your own mind your what would become
strong sh yeah your ability to to to
turn on the fire alarm when your mind
starts wandering okay so that's the
positive thing what's the negative
thing
notter yeah you're just aware that
you're
irritated you see what I mean you're
like wow look irritated thoughts
you know you're wow look my mind is
irritated you know but it doesn't fix it
you see uh probably it's a necessary
first step right you have to know your
mind's out of control to control it but
uh okay so that's our criticism of that
meditation it's nice to sit and watch
your mind thoughts pop up that's okay
but it's not going to fix the problem
okay it's a first step and and that's
okay all of these meditations I think to
get in this book you had to have
something good about your
meditation to get kicked out of to get
to get your butt kicked in this book is
an honor and you have to have a decent
uh you have to have a decent fake
meditation okay now second
one and this is worth
$100 who's my
Treasurer Peter okay I'll give you like
a pile of money before class then you
have to give it out okay keep a list if
you lose a few names it's
okay uh
he he's a human computer look over
there chuku Lum chuku Lum you guys who
spent seven years going to 20,000 pages
of vria at Diamond
Mountain sometimes I think no one ever
heard anything
water you should pay
me Sha
Sha death
cha this lady with the the white hair
100 bucks you got to pay me
back take me out to
dinner
okay okay this is a tantric practice
okay this is a hard tantric practice but
he refers to it so I can talk about it
uh now the next meditation is that some
people say if you watch your thoughts
fade away okay the first guys want to
watch your thoughts pop up the other gu
say watching your thoughts fade way is
is chuku L say say
chuku l and this is a very important
tantric principle okay and he mentioned
it so I can talk about it chuku means
the DH body the Dharma body so the
Buddhist supposedly when you become a
Buddha you have three or four different
bodies okay which are not real bodies
they're just called bodies it means
parts of you okay so call them the four
parts of you
okay uh chuku means what
I know but emptiness of the other bodies
yeah you can say The Emptiness of of you
after Nick becomes Buddha Nick like St
Nicholas
uh yeah the emptiness of of Nick is is
is the core of that Buddha okay and
we'll talk about it okay what's
the yeah then there's the Paro say Paro
l l l par long
what's
par yeah after you die Spirit life up to
49 days okay in the spirit realm par uh
is the
lonu body yeah the body in heaven okay
the heaven body so according to Buddhism
when you become a Buddha part of you
Parts in a heaven there's a part of you
that Parts your physical body in heaven
this you know
the kind of Brad body you see in the
paintings of of a this not so bad but uh
some kind of divine form right and you
hang out in your own Heaven uh with this
form it's called lonu which means body
of
enjoyment and that's compared to the ble
okay that's compared to the ble because
death itself in a tantric presentation
is kind of like entering emptiness okay
it's kind of like entering emptiness and
then uh you can ride it if you're
trained okay you can ride the death
experience uh to emptiness if you're
trained properly and we did it uh in the
larm roomm course for I don't know 10
days and I'm not doing it
over for another year or
two and uh you've been through all that
but you can
as you die you can carry it uh to a
higher reality okay and that's called
chuku okay using death as a ticket Lam
means what for $100 oh no you did it
already I'm sorry Lam means path path
okay K him means uh use it it means to
carry something like a donkey would care
something but it it it it me means to
use the death experience for something
higher transform it it means to
transform it okay into a path okay to
use it as a path okay so that's chuk
okay what's the next
one
par use the B experience as taking on a
a a super beautiful sexy angels's body
why does it relate to parle to the ble
you take on an ephemeral body during the
B you take on a temporary form you take
on like a spirit form it's almost
Angelic in that you can't cut it with a
knife and things like that it's almost
it's similar to uh this rainbow body in
in the heaven okay it's it's similar to
this kind of
Exquisite uh Heavenly form
okay which if you put your hand to it
you your hand would go through with
which is why they call a rainbow so if
you ever tried to walk to a rainbow it
just kind of takes you in and you never
yeah okay so that's part of l l and then
what's
K I know but come on
Nick yeah to yeah amination party okay
so every
Buddha said you got it right but I
didn't bet anything okay uh every Buddha
has the one of the reasons become a buha
is that you have the power
to send avatars send bodies to other
worlds take you can be I like to say you
can be on the bus in La next to an
elderly lady helping her and at the same
time you can be in Beijing as someone's
peing dog and making that elderly person
happy you see and but multiplied times
countless billions at the same time so
you have the power to send down bodies
it's almost as if you are reborn every
second okay K
say l okay so now you got the principle
right and you have to be
extremely well educated in the classics
to read this poem cuz he just says Chum
he doesn't explain it and uh there's no
commentary he he never wrote A
Commentary so and what he's what he's
saying is he's trying to compare it to
the opposite of the last meditation who
can tell
me just watching thought that no that
was watching what yeah good watching
your thoughts
fade and and there's a school that
developed
inbet of just trying to bring up random
thoughts during meditation and watch
them
fade and then each time they fade you go
through the death process you go through
ch to okay cool is it useless no I think
it's
sexy I have I have designed DCI
meditations on the ones he's complaining
about uh to be frank like present moment
meditation was one of his first
complaints uh so yeah they're useful
they're okay you can use it it's okay
it's all right but it's incomplete
there's something it's beautiful it
could be useful it has problems okay it
has some problems now you want to know
one of the problems okay and by the way
I'm going to I am going to give you a
break and in about 20 minutes so stop
complaining in your head
uh this is a big theme throughout his
whole poem is that your mind is mistaken
all the time okay not
sometimes in fact in
prasanga you never have a until you see
emptiness directly
never okay you never saw anything
correctly in your whole life physical
mental
anything everything was mistaken poison
okay so he's what he's saying here okay
ready every time you're aware of your
own
mind and you're not thinking about the
emptiness of it you are po throwing more
poison in the
well you are you are
reinforcing a a bad habit that has been
going for time with no beginning every
time you get irritated at
someone it has to be that you're
misunderstanding them if you
misunderstand them you are
reinforcing the state of mind that put
you in this world okay it's scary you
see what it means is every hour that
goes by
that you don't have an internal
conversation debate about something you
are
reinforcing your negativities okay and
they'll get stronger and stronger okay
it's it's uh nasty what do you call
that perous pernicious
exactly it's
nasty okay it gets worse just being
alive makes you a worse person how's
that okay if you don't have Angel
talking in your head okay and that's
what he's saying he says that's a cute
idea you go to Tantra in your
meditation you imagine as the thought
disappears into emptiness that this is
the emptiness body of a Buddha and it's
it's kind of cool you know but in the
end you are just watching your thoughts
and your thoughts are wrong okay your
thoughts are infected and the longer you
watch the worst you'll get okay watching
your mind without thinking about where
it's coming from poisons The Watcher and
the mind being washed okay got it it's
depressing all
right
okay let's go to the next depressing
one
uh I don't know why he goes there okay
he's been there he's going to go there
again and I took a the four spaces
meditation came from here okay the four
wrong ideas about space okay so
emptiness
meditation is sometimes called namat
Tabu space space likee meditation you
know so that name itself caused a lot of
problems people close their eyes and try
to see blue and then more advanced
people close their eyes and try to see
black and then more advanced people
close their eyes and try to see empty
space yeah the space in which the chair
is standing which is more subtle can
only be seen with your third eye okay
you can only be seen with with logic
clear thinking I like to call it clear
thinking nowadays sometimes uh okay so
he's covered that okay I don't know why
he brings it up here but he says look
there's some people who said as you
watch the thought
disappear reflect on how it's not
physical
because that's a negative and Emptiness
is a
negative is emptiness a negative sure
yeah give me a credit card example
Discover Card tell the whole story make
it right I got taking John Brady to Cina
so I say John come on you never did that
that's okay okay
okay yeah come on come on don't be shy
so I I take John bray to uh to
Cina and uh and we have explain whatca
okay so in the village O Creek we have
like one restaurant One
Restaurant um and it's called cuchina
rustia right it's full name and it's a
really nice restaurant and we um we go
there pretty often and so um llama John
Brady's doing something amazing for acip
like paying me and
so I'm like oh let me use some of this
money to take Lama John out and so we
take him to the I take him to the
restaurant and we have a good time and
we laugh and cry and
everything and it comes time to pay the
bill so I'm like oh no no no llama I
wouldn't dream of you paying so I go in
my pocket to go for my credit card but
here's the thing the credit card that I
was going to go for was a Discover Card
you B it oh changed your shirt you
changed your oh oh yeah so I go go for
it and I only have like one pair of
pants if you guys hadn't noticed already
after 5 years two pairs of Fant and so I
put the wrong ones on so I'm like oh
don't worry I'll pay for it and I go I
start searching I'm like uh uh uh and I
don't have the credit card on me yeah
and so so that's kind of empty that's
like emptiness cuz it's an absence of
something but if you really understand
emptiness you realize that the thing
that Emptiness is empty of never could
exist in the first place so the thing
about the card that I was going for is
that it was a Discover Card which is not
really a credit card
anyway all right yeah so MD
means something's not there that you
thought was there but the trick is the
thing you thought was there should be
something that couldn't exist it has to
be something that couldn't exist okay so
thinking that it's a good meditation to
think about how your thoughts are not
physical is a problem why physical
physical exists yeah you're canceling
something that does exist
okay Peter you and Maria going to do the
two husbands thing
can can you no you want to she's like
no you don't have to be you you want to
Quick can I do it
quick no only if you want to you don't
have to you don't have
to you don't have
to you don't have to but it'd be
nice I need another
husband come on quick quick
not a
bu yeah you want to try yeah yeah do it
for the do it for people not for not cuz
it's comfortable okay uh wait who's
going to be the other husband JB wants
to okay you guys want to take a moment
and
prepare you want to no it's totally up
to you
guys uh you get it ready you tell me
when you're ready okay and I'll keep
stalling all
right
uh okay so if the thing was ever there
and you cancel it that's not medit
that's not emptiness okay isn't a
physical thought the same thing as a
pink elephant it doesn't exist uh that's
true too you're yeah that's kind of a
cute argument I'll give you some
Monopoly money for that uh you guys
ready yes okay can you just be loud or
maybe Maria use the
microphone okay all right go okay don't
be shy I'm not
he's we need two children also right
yeah who want to be two children
actually it's always
those do you want to be two children
they're
busy can two children volunteer who sit
in these two chairs yeah thank you
oh well the story is about how do we
create things right and it it
incorporates both emptiness what is not
there and how things do exist so um I'm
the wife these are two husbands I'm
coming home one
night after a long day at work and I
even bought food for the dinner and I'm
just happy that I come home to my
husband and the only thing that I really
want is a hug because I'm just exhausted
and so as I come home I open the door I
step in I'm looking for my husband
husband I'll can I it later okay to
before before I came
home two days before that 3 days before
that the evening before I have a
assignment at my
work my boss tells me that the next day
in the morning I have to be earlier at
work because there's a Skype call
probably with the Germans and so I come
home and I tell my two children who are
very attentative and ask them can you
please tomorrow morning get up 1 hour
earlier dress up put your shoes
on put your clothes on and then be ready
to go at 7 and not at 8 is that okay yes
otherwise we assign you for
adoption she does care anyway okay they
say yes they're super happy about that
next day in the morning I wake up 1 hour
earlier I get ready to leave for the
office I come down I get into the room
and what do I
see the two children jumping on the bed
they're not dressed they're not ready to
go and I got really frustrated and
because I forget the angel in my head
that we're going to learn about today
I'm saying you two are the stupidest
kids in
Sedona and then I wrap them up go to the
office and forget about the whole thing
2 days later or a week later I come home
to the situation I described before when
I'm just tired and exhausted from work
buying dinner and my expectation as I
open the door is that my husband is
going to give me at least a hug and as I
open the door and I step in and I'm kind
of waiting for the hug you're
stupid my husband who's not doing
anything
else but except to give me hugs in the
evening sometimes is not even do that
anymore and I'm get totally upset
because I didn't do
anything and that's the example like to
discovery card where it is is it true
that I didn't do
anything no right and what's the
connection today you yeled to children
so I assume where we're going tonight I
don't know but the angel in the head
would probably have to tell me in that
very difficult and crucial moment that
anything that happens to me must have a
cause and when I step in there we there
and
I expect the hug and he's saying you are
stupid I have to
remember that there are two husbands in
the kitchen right why are the
[Music]
two in this case it's okay you had two
children
because because it's me it's you because
it's me yeah you're you're the jerk
telling yourself that you were oh I see
that's one that's one
possibility any other ideas why are
there two husbands there because one
doesn't exist exactly one does not exist
right there's one husband in the kitchen
who do does exist and one husband who
doesn't exist what's the husband that
does
exist yells say again the one that comes
from yelling at the kid exactly is that
husband also yelling at me yes yes so
there is a yelling husband it does exist
but it comes from because I have created
him in the past how about the second one
the one with the long blonde hair
beautiful husband that doesn't exist at
all right because that's a husband that
could exist from his side in this case
it could be a husband that is not
created by my own actions and which one
of the two husbands do I get angry about
the long blonde hair the long blonde
hair husband who doesn't exist at all
because husbands don't have long blonde
hair
right okay
sometimes they don't so what is the
right reaction in this case what is the
F effect of the angel in my mind when I
understand this the theory of these
teachings and can apply them in the
Practical moment which is so difficult
for at least me I get into I get home I
forgot the story of the kids long time
ago and it doesn't matter at that moment
I step in I expect something good to
happen stupid
and this you know this is time slowed
down I'm like wait a moment this is not
nice I don't like it what should I do
now I really hate it
actually and if I have the angel in my
mind the angel will say because you
really hate it you're just going to
accept it and you're not going to yal
back you're going to go to the real
husband and say I'm sorry I had a bad
day that's okay
honey and all is good thank
[Music]
[Applause]
you yeah so the point of
the which meditation was it
13 kind of
13 no
14 anyway I forget it uh uh yeah it's
kind of half of 13 okay second half of
13 second it's verse number 119 because
the guy went on a detour and said that
Emptiness is that your thoughts are not
physical okay but that's that can't be
emptiness because physical things do
exist okay so emptiness means and and
think about the difference
okay if someone called you stupid in the
kitchen when you came home and you got
mad at your husband and then he turned
around and it turns out to be your
neighbor
right what happens to your
anger yeah it just
uh I like to give the example it's kind
of depressing example because I actually
been there but uh so your girlfriend or
your partner is is on the phone like
this you know you come in and she's
like and you're like what are you doing
and and she's like oh nothing you know
and you're like by the way this is a
long time ago okay uh and and you're
like well who you texting and you're
like oh nothing nothing you know and
then you get kind of you start to worry
that she has another boyfriend right and
then you uh so you're cool though and
you don't say anything but that night
when she's asleep you get the phone and
and you check right and it turns out to
be she was buying you a birthday present
on Amazon and it was a secret okay and
that's why she hid the phone okay so
where is the new
boyfriend yeah completely non-existent
you see what I mean so then how do you
feel about
him you just feel
stupid okay like uh so we're not talking
about that you picked up her you thought
it was Fred and you pick up the phone
and it was joh
instead and you were slightly mistaken
okay it's not a case in tibetan of
mayin it's not a case of mistaken
identity it's not that you thought she
was texting this guy who might be her
boyfriend but she was texting a
different guy who who who might be her
boyfriend okay that's not emptiness
emptiness is you find out she was
ordering you a birthday present on
Amazon and the whole boyfriend thing
what do you call that dissipates
diffuses it's how do you make it more
dramatic than
that
disolves impls is pretty good it just
dissolves that's emptiness okay and
that's what it does to your heart yeah
you're just oh man that's so weird I
thought was a boyfriend oh she bought me
a birthday present you know like it's a
totally
opposite thing okay so if you're going
to do an emptiness meditation
on someone who irritates you the result
should be some kind of
joy and not some kind of oh mistaken
identity it's not not who I thought it
was that's not it it's that he dissolves
the problem dissolves okay if you are
trying to deal with a problem as a
Buddhist and you're trying to use
emptiness and that problem doesn't
dissolve in front of you you aren't you
don't have an angel in your head and you
don't understand Buddhism
and you're not
practicing okay this at this level okay
we're not talking watch your breath
Buddhism is it
Buddhism it is Buddha taught watching
breath okay what's it called there's
some Sans
name in tibetan it's called okay say
josha 350 ad Master vasu Watch your
breath okay that's okay that's a
Buddhist Meditation but it's not going
to make you happy it's not going to make
the guy dissolve the boyfriend dissolve
you see and and you feel like this
intense uh relaxation after the
boyfriend dissolves you see so if if you
don't get it
straight the angel emptiness meditation
where the person who's irritating you or
the obstacle in your life doesn't
dissolve you're not doing meditation on
emptiness you're you're doing some
lesser
meditation okay and you're not really uh
complete
Buddhist okay so now you have new thing
to be depressed about okay uh we got
five minutes I'm going to give you a
break okay so don't
stress
uh now bets are we on or not did you get
my email we're on okay now uh we have a
translation team upstairs 10 primary
translators about 80 secondary
translators and they
are translating the classics and the
book now goes to a famous emptiness
meditation called chck say chick
to
CH and recently up in
the enlightenment Cavern
uh B's text venerable uta's text reached
his next Point okay so he's going to
talk about a famous emptiness meditation
called
Chik uh neither one nor many neither one
nor many okay very famous but her book
the presentation of it is the best
presentation I ever saw in in I don't
know 40 years or 35 years okay it's the
best so I she's supposed to teach it
tomorrow and I said can I borrow it and
you teach something else and she
graciously
said Okay okay so I thought we since
we're going through this text so fast we
might want to take a
detour uh to her
book and it's the best uh presentation I
ever saw of this particular emptiness
meditation okay so it's called Chik
now it's it's called one or many The
Emptiness of one or many and it's very
famous and his presentation in her book
Tony Lama is the best I've ever seen and
uh I just want to steal it and she said
go for it so thank you for that and
uh I really wanted to do it so I'm I'm
grateful to you I'll I'll give
I'll I'll pay you back somehow someday
day okay so here we
[Music]
go I'm just going to teach it straight
from the text okay and we went through
it and she translated it and it's
amazing okay so uh here we go we're
going to an emptiness meditation text
this is her text from the authors from
1648 to 1721 if I'm not
mistaken maybe I am mistaken 1675 1675
to
1748 I was mistaken anyway it's about
300 years ago and a beautiful
presentation is meditation
now guess why he brings up that
meditation
here because there
something beautiful yeah someone's
messing it up okay someone's trying to
do this ancient emptiness meditation and
they're doing it slightly wrong okay
that's his thing right he's going to
present it slightly wrong but you can't
appreciate it if you don't know it in
the first place so I have to go through
it you ready and and this is the best
presentation I ever saw that's a good
place to take a break
right
uh well Okay one minute
yeah uh so
there's something wrong about
stuff uh like when I look at gil I I
look at her arms and her head and her
legs and her torso and I my mind puts it
together as a person okay this is uh her
Parts uh is she one is she one person
yes or no looks like okay but how do I
see the one person I got to have Parts
there's got to be Parts you can't see a
person without looking at their parts
first you know you look one arm other
arm one leg other leg head torso okay
person okay
so we're trying to prove that there's no
one okay why is that done before proving
there's no
many that's option
left who said that yeah many are made of
ones many's are made of ones if there's
no one gu in the chair there can't be
more than one okay now if there's
neither one G nor multiple G there's
no gal okay that's the classic proof and
it sounds stupid but because it's so
profound okay if I can prove that
there's not one computer up here on the
lecturn okay and then I allow you to
discuss is there two okay if I can prove
there's not one then proving there's not
two is easy proving there's not more
than one is easy okay cuz there's not
one cuz if you don't have one you can't
have two Okay so so if there's one
object in the universe which doesn't
have emptiness okay then there can't be
sorry if there's no object in the
universe that doesn't have emptiness
there can't be multiple objects in the
universe okay got it so the many just
cancel it now okay forget it I mean I'll
say it again if this is not empty okay
and I say did I have 10 of those up here
would there be something something empty
say no I mean cuz one's not empty okay
so all I have to prove is one so forget
the many okay we're going to go to the
one we're going to come back to this
meditation tonight I guess depending on
how long you PP I don't know or what
number you have to do uh but we're going
to come back and see how you can miss
meditate that's a good word for this
book uh yeah how can you mism meditate
okay and uh on on this emptiness
meditation this is one of the most
famous emptiness one of the top five
emptiness meditations okay so let's do
it when you get back come back by
8:30 all right so the to appreciate the
next meditations in the book uh you have
to understand this ancient argument for
emptiness okay to understand that
argument of emptiness there are many
many presentations but the one in 's
book is the best one I ever seen and I'm
stealing it
shamelessly okay so on our D TR so he's
going to prove that things have parts
and then we'll talk about why if things
have Parts they have to be empty okay
got it so he's very thorough which is
why we love him how many of our books
are from him Ben
Su sug no not suang no Stanley Stanley
Ben and you and UD
three what your commentary yeah so say
we we're trying say this is a great uh
llama called chony llama from about 300
years ago right human computer yeah okay
so anyway here's his way of proving that
things have Parts okay and he does it uh
DCI level s thing he does a DCI level s
thing DCI level 7 is uh you go through
all the categories of
existence okay so we're going to take a
quick trip through all the categories of
existence okay we're going to prove why
each one of them has to have Parts when
we finish that we'll prove why if it has
Parts it has to be
empty okay ready here we go so we start
with physical stuff okay and
uh science says that uh this microphone
is made up of small
atoms uh of like call it carbon and iron
and oxygen and atoms okay I like to
teach it this way
atam is a Sanskrit a means not like a
atheist or
apathetic uh agnostic where do you find
that you're brilliant who's brilliant
one of those guys okay yeah this is DC
level 7 so the definition of existence
in Buddhism is anything you can perceive
with a correct perception then it's real
okay then it exists there are two kinds
of uh things in the universe those that
exist and change and those that exist
and don't change okay those are the two
two divisions of all things in the
universe uh who's teaching the Obby Dar
tomorrow I oh good luck honey I'm
sorry very famous the opening lines
of and
99.999% of stuff in the world is in the
left side the red left side and then
only three things uh are in the right
side okay classically and then uh
changing things
uh you got physical things and then you
got things that change that aren't
physical or mental and then you got
mental things okay this is the outline
of Buddhism uh outline of the universe
okay if we can prove each one has parts
then we prove that all things are empty
I'll take you there okay so don't get
nervous
tah she's not nervous okay here we go uh
so
physical things we're going to start
with the leftand Box okay physical
things do they have parts and we go to
uh you know we go to to stuff has the
chair has legs has arms okay and then
the plastic has molecules and the
molecules have atoms okay and the atoms
have core and spin and other parts okay
uh
sub subatomic particles but uh at a
means not right t means
divisible and the word that comes from
it in English is Temple Temple because
the temple was divided from the village
in the old days so it was called set
apart Temple means set apart from the
village and so atam means cannot be
split the thing which cannot be
split which which in science is
reflected in the period IC table of the
elements okay meaning element so what
does element mean in science it
means this
substance uh is the smallest you can get
and it retains its qualities okay so
iron is still hard and I don't know
oxygen is still Airy and things like
that okay so if you break it H2O into H
and O it loses the quality of you can't
drink it anymore okay it's so when you
go below an element uh you lose the
identity of the thing and that's why
it's called an element that's why
there's only I don't know 16 something
like that uh elements because a piece of
it won't act like the whole anymore okay
like a quirk all quirks are the same all
electrons protons neutrons act the same
it's only in a certain configuration in
certain kind of shells in the atomic
structure that it will act as an element
okay when you take away one peace it
doesn't act the same anymore okay so
that's what element means that's the
idea of an atom okay
then then there's an idea that an atom
cannot be split we we now we split atoms
but you cannot split it and still retain
its identity that's not possible okay it
won't be hard anymore or it won't flow
anymore okay so atam then he he wants to
talk about atomic theory
now this is considered the crudest form
of philosophy in Buddhism is atomic
theory it's considered the most stupid
one the lowest one and it's the one that
we believe it's science okay so stuff is
made of little pieces and those pieces
have an identity okay and then in the
ancient times they say they are the
smallest thing they cannot be divided
they are a t m okay so uh so here's Chun
Lama okay he says okay let's take this
atom that you can't split anymore cuz it
wouldn't act the same so it would it has
to
be one thing but it can't be divisible
right so then he says the way he puts it
is in his in your book is the so you
have an atom here then you have an adom
to the west and you have an adom to the
east okay so I I was going to bring some
tennis balls but I didn't have
time uh and I didn't have any tennis
balls but
but uh so three tennis balls okay and
and and chony llama is like does the
middle ball touch the ball on on this
side yes or no yes now does the ball on
this side touch the ball on this side no
okay which means that this ball must
have a right side and a left side right
because there's a plate if if this ball
touched this ball where this ball touch
this ball then this Ball's inside of
this ball got it okay you all right I'll
say it again three balls uh if this ball
touches this ball right and then if this
ball touches this ball then it would
have to touch it here and then this ball
would have to be in the same place as
this ball okay so the one on the left
would I'll be in the place of the one in
the middle okay for the one on the left
to touch the one on the right got it
then the guy says come out that's stupid
the one in the middle is is blocking it
you see the one over here can't touch
the one over here cuz there's one in the
middle don't be stupid it's not
necessary that this one has to touch
this one cuz this one's in the middle
and he says yeah then it's not a t
then it has a right side and left side
then you can split it you see okay got
it and that's all and in In classical
Buddhism you'd say four directions and
up and down six directions and he'd say
it can't be okay so either this one is
occupying the same space as this one
okay okay got it then if you piled up
atoms to make the chair how big would
the chair be
it couldn't be bigger than an atom okay
if Adams take the same space then you
can't make a chair out of it if you can
make a chair out of it you don't have at
atoms okay then there's no
elements or oh no no G they are little
bosss and and they're unique identity
they have a little unique identity right
right mhm but when you split them they
don't okay so okay so the left side of
the atom acts the same as the right
side does a part of the atom act the
same as another part of the atom
sure know but then it can't be hard
anymore because neutrons are generic all
of them have neutrons all they have
electrons all they have protons they all
have spin they all have cork they all
have
it but they aren't hard okay you got to
have the whole thing they have hard okay
and and if the atoms are only touching
pieces of each other they can't be hard
anymore okay got it unless they're in
the same ball in which case the chair is
one out of
one okay now if I'm the guarder I will
say something's going
on okay and you just never thought about
it and I'm not trying to convince you a
Buddhist philosophy I'm not I'm saying
there's something weird going on there's
something not possible going on that's
all okay now let's go to some other
[Music]
box I think he goes to the one in the
middle
next yeah okay so there's stuff in the
world that changes that's not your mind
and it's not physical and there's a
couple of examples there's not a lot of
stuff in that box one is
oral okay orl crawled into this box the
middle box okay the person is in this
box because Earl is not Earl's body and
Earl is not Earl's mind okay Earl says I
have a headache it means he's he doesn't
say I am a headache I mean he is a
headache but no he doesn't say I am a
headache so he's not his mind but he has
a mind right so he he says I have a
headache that means Earl is not his mind
and then he says or I I broke my finger
then that means he owns a finger but the
finger is not Earl got it Earl has a
body Earl has a mind Earl the concept
Earl is in the middle box okay people
are in the middle box okay give me
another thing that's in the middle
box seeds mental seeds Okay when Peter
yelled at his two
kids how was the seed planted kic seed
Vasa when you heard yeah when you hear
yourself talk it makes an imprint on
your brain it makes an imprint on your
mind that becomes a seed after like an
hour or two okay that becomes a Karma
seed mental seed Karma same thing
okay are those M yes or no and tell me
why for
$100 they're not mine not mine because
they not
aware who said it first know good okay
100 bucks for him
Peter don't tell V okay she says it's
crass in the United States okay but I
find greed everyone
resp yeah people always give a good
answer okay so what he said was seeds
stay in the mind and there's a common
mistake made by Buddhists who hear that
they will say well the the seed is in
the mind so the seed is part of the mind
but that's a mistake okay and the
classic argument is that the seed
doesn't know anything you see so the
definition of mind for for
zering in INE ineffable and aware and
seeds are not aware they don't think
they don't feel they don't have
Impressions okay so seeds belong in the
mind but they're not mental stuff and
they're obviously not physical okay why
because you have billions of seeds in
your heart chakra and you didn't get
your chest didn't explode
okay right I me you have countless Karma
seeds in your heart chakra but they
don't you know pile up they're not
physical they are a state of
potential okay karma karma okay another
example come on chony Lama example in
his
text time who said that you are so
awesome you I don't know you're probably
listening in one of those videos uh yeah
time itself time time is in there it's
not physical it's not mental it's a
concept concepts are mostly there okay
now chony Lama wants to take some of
those Concepts and prove that they have
parts that's our game today we're trying
to finish it by 9:00 I don't know what's
going to happen we're trying to finish
one verse out of
110 okay so here we go uh why why does
the person according to Tony Lama have
parts
I don't know if you remember they stand
up they sit down they walk around Nick
walks Nick sits Nick stands so Nick has
Parts okay there's different aspects of
Nick phases yeah he has Parts whatever
okay so that's the person for Zer do
time has Parts
because yeah past present future but
more
interestingly if
yeah Mo if you perceive if you think of
time as tennis balls okay then there's
got to be a ass end of the first moment
and a front end of the first moment you
see what I mean and the butt end of the
first moment has to touch the front end
of the second moment so moments have
pieces also got it because they're
sequential time time goes on in sequence
so the back end of the first moment has
to be touching the front end of the
second moment that means every moment's
divisible if the front
end if the back end of the first moment
you ready doesn't touch the front end of
the second moment and all of the first
moment touches the second moment and
they're not and you don't want to talk
about front end and back end of a moment
then then all reality is one moment and
it just ends in one moment okay got it
it's easy it's like the atom thing
okay all right mental things this sexy
super sexy what is say you remember I I
read it over again today twice
so has
realized nice nice there's only two
kinds of Minds in the universe either
you saw EMP this or you didn't you have
the angel in your
mind perfectly or you don't and and
that's all he he says another thing I
forget what he says one more
[Music]
thing time time of the flow of the
mind okay and he that's okay same
principle okay the time of the flow of
the mind but anyway the mind you have
parts of your mind that understand
emptiness to some extent and then you
have Parts in your mind that don't so
your mind has Parts okay ready now we go
more deep which is why I like his
presentation I told you now the diamond
shaped Red Box okay things that exist
but don't change give me some especially
Abida yeah empty space okay is one
example yeah the two kinds of sensation
and fact is close you're second
school huh
emptiness okay okay three things that
don't change okay let let's do the most
easy one first and then we'll go to more
difficult ones okay so
uh the emptiness the empty space that
the chair occupies okay got it so the
chair even if I pull the chair over here
there will still be a place where it was
okay empty space so that doesn't change
as long as the chair is there it doesn't
change if you pull the chair over here
the empty space Also remains you can
occupy it or you
can absent it vacate vacate it vac
exactly but it don't change in either
case if this whole world explodes what
happened with Trump and the guy how' It
Go not well no but did it mess up or was
it just like nothing sometimes you have
to walk away that's it
all I just wondered if I'm going to be
gardening tomorrow or not that's the
thing why
not so it went
okay anyway okay I can tell you that's
why it wasn't in the news okay uh I
can't get it from either yeah occupy the
space so the space doesn't change now
does the space have
Parts yeah there's the two spaces here
okay there's a space that that chair is
in and there's a space that that chair
is in so space in general has
Parts okay there's the spa yeah
directions but he says it more sexy he
says the
space that the chair that this chair
vacates and the space that that chair
vacates when you pull them both out are
different space
spaces okay so space in general has
Parts okay empty space has Parts okay
and it's cool next
one the two Sensations okay sensation
what's a sensation how you going to
Define it end of something stops forever
not something though well your mental
Affliction specifically yeah a negative
State of Mind okay so Buddhism is
fascinating the whole purpose of
Buddhism is can you get to a place where
you where your kid or your partner
cannot make you angry ever again like is
it even theoretically
possible Rick's like I don't know she's
like hitting him see there it is right
there
uh but he always
smiles he's got that Buddhism thing down
uh yeah two Sensations okay if we go
Abby dway if we go Abby dway uh it means
the the permanent ending of a negativity
you can never be made angry again I
remember when I was a kid it was my
little brother's goal to make me angry
and he would actually say that he'd say
I'm going to make you angry today I'd
say okay try and he usually could do it
okay
uh why two kinds of
sensation what's the two in the Ali
Dharma during meditation that happens
temporarily the one that happens perfect
you can say it that way that's one way
to say it uh you stop your
gross thought processes that's a
sensation and then at a deeper level you
see emptiness and you stop anger forever
for example something like that but
there's another way
uhis yeah meaning okay if you understand
emptiness theoretically from the
pen uh you achieve
whatam which means uh if you die today
you cannot go to a bad place it's not
it's
not Universe
possible it's not uh possible that you
can be born in a bad place okay if you
understand
emptiness theoretically correctly well
from a pen
uh not in
meditation uh you cannot be born in a
bad place so you guys should learn how
to teach the pen you should teach the
pen you should teach it to people people
on the airplane sitting next to you who
ask you what you do I do it I do it
because I think maybe I saved this
person from the hells you know you know
why not he just thinks I'm weird it's
okay I'm used to that okay all right so
that's okay and then and then of course
there's the seeing emptiness directly
okay all right
now let's take the
sensations why would it have
Parts the ending of a negativity would
have Parts
why different Sensations yeah no
different negativities look I got an end
of my jealousy look I have an end of my
anger look I have an end of my desire
okay these are separate entities the
okay unchanging they will never come
back they will never change okay the
loss permanent loss sensation is a weird
word right you don't use sensation in
English we had a sensation of my
girlfriend and
me something like that okay but it means
a permanent loss you can't like John and
me's hair okay not I don't know maybe
we'll come back but I'm not holding my
breath uh okay
stem cells yeah we'll work on it uh okay
so anyway that's a permanent loss okay
but there are different permanent losses
that's all so there's parts to permanent
loss got
it now we just have to go The Emptiness
and we're done and it's right on time
okay I'm going to stop in 4 minutes
anyone can tell me the wait for
$100 don't tell me okay
Peter raised his hand before I ask a
question it's like I'll take a shot
gisha no I'm not it's not that
easy okay I want you to explain to me
why emptiness can have parts and in
doing it I want you to explain why
there's another kind of idea about
Indians having Parts which is wrong
and you guys had it upstairs I have one
when the snow hit the because emptiness
of a thing is only one
emptiness uh wait you weren't in the
class forget it it's impossible no this
is very difficult come
on chony llama's example was
faulty
right yeah give me more give me more you
get up to 20
bucks 19 18 yeah when he talks about
emptiness come on The Emptiness of you
can split it if you guys get it right
but it might take the whole
year which means The Emptiness of a
vessel space
within okay but that doesn't count
because it's not Place yeah he said that
space in a in a coffee cup right that's
on that desk and the space in a coffee
cup that's on that desk okay is that
emptiness no it's just the distance
between two things okay don't think
that's emptiness that's a big mistake it
doesn't help you you cannot build I
don't know the largest diamond Joy comp
in the world based on how white is a
cup it doesn't that's not emptiness okay
emptiness should be something you can
use to make cool stuff to make anything
happen okay if it's not that it's not
emptiness okay empty is supposed to be
the key of the
universe okay so that was the wrong one
what's the right one Nick had it 33
bucks each 30 cents for UDA cuz it's her
text there's
many yeah why
because okay she gets 33 you're
representing
her tell
Aaron
okay more oh I should say yeah come on
no she asked me she asked you to do it
for her she'll pay you 30 I'll pay her
okay emptiness each so where were we
each has it own emptiness yeah good and
uh there's no just emptiness that would
exist independent of a thing to be empty
something has to be empty yeah last
thing okay 100 bucks again don't tell V
don't even tell her I didn't don't tell
her I told you not to tell
her
her okay this another 100 bucks let me
get the question
[Music]
right how does that relate to the two
husbands when you second husband the
second husband is the distance between
things doesn't exist I mean it's you
don't say
anything oh I
know it was never there so you can't
even say that it's empty that that's
okay you could say that that's not
bad okay so
50/50 now okay last thing then we're
done for tonight and I'm ending on time
the angel in your head has to say that
was never there in the first place she
was buying me a gift on Amazon there was
no boyfriend it has to dissolve that's
emptiness you see the person you thought
was there the husband who decided to be
mean to
you say it the classic way
could never exist could never exist
never will never will exist doesn't
exist no never existed in the past
cannot exist now and will never exist in
the person in the future but I'll bet
you $500 you'll get upset
tomorrow okay yeah yeah cuz we know but
we can't do it and I'm talking to myself
too you know I've had a rough week that
way and
uh it don't exist the person who's
getting you
upset who decided to say something to
you don't exist never existed okay got
ITA I've been I've been struggling with
with this concept of of dissolving
because that uh uh implies it was there
impes that it was there yeah that's a
Gooding about um if it's like a mirage
describe it to me in the case of the uh
telephone describe the process in your
mind you no you she falls asleep you
wait for her to get asleep you find out
her secret code you sneak around the bed
you keep down low you reach up and get
the phone and you then you open the
phone right and you want to read the
message from the boyfriend if you do all
that she should break up with
you no I'm just saying no you tell me
cuz during the grabbing of the phone
during the waiting for her to sleep
during the sneaking around the bed you
have something in your mind you have a
image of a
boyfriend yeah whole but the the hero of
the story The Villain is there you know
he's slightly more handsome than you
he's got more hair you know and then and
uh he's strong here you know and then
you you open her phone and you see
Amazon order number 57 for I don't know
new
bicycle and that was her last thing that
she was texting exactly that
moment so what you tell me what happens
to the
boyfriend but she doesn't want to say
dissolve cuz she her position is that he
was never there number one it wasn't
there and number two it doesn't get
gradually gradually smaller smaller
it's totally replaced with the TR thing
yeah it poof let's say poof let's say it
poofs
po okay
[Music]
agree if you get the angel if this class
causes you to introduce the angel into
your
head then no one one can make you
unhappy
anymore it's not
possible we're not talking about
treating anger we're not talking about
making it better we're talking about no
make Angry anyway that's what I'm saying
yeah that's what I'm trying to say so
he's in the end the whole poem is to
criticize lesser
antidotes he wants po
okay he wants boyfriend gone he doesn't
want oh try to deal with the boyfriend
or try to understand the boyfriend also
wants somebody or you know he's not
talking about that he's saying you know
and then then you know you just feel
stupid because you thought she was
texting
somebody yes irritate me there you're
going to make me break it in the first
minute after the talk okay you
didn't what so for okay for the two
husbands yeah to for to actually be a
antidot to Samara yeah wouldn't you in
the end have to realize that the person
you who got upset in the first place
never was there to get that's true I
would say that that's pretty subtle
that's pretty subtle life right but I
think it would be the yeah but
Bel you and what you hold to me you uh
the the definition of the first link of
The Wheel of Life is holds to me and
mine and the husband is mine
no no Tac what's not mine if you're nice
your husband's not yours Tac no the mine
of course is a part not to no no no
outside things are part of
you it depends on school yeah well my
school okay Hector you want to do this
thing yeah okay we have a tradition to
offer a a mandala at the end of class
and it uh it you you can do it this way
if you don't know the finger thing or
you can look stupid and try to figure it
out uh but uh no it's kind of cute in
class when
somebody's just learn it from somebody
but you can do it this way and it you
are offering the world okay the point is
this is the payment of the class this
the traditional payment of the class
money is not enough you have to offer a
perfect world what's happening in a
perfect
world everyone know everyone has the
angel in their head so so at the end of
this class as payment for the class you
are offering a your imagination of a
world where every single person has the
angel in their head and all the
boyfriends went
poof I mean except for the one you want
[Music]
okay sh
go
[Music]
probably
not I mean on your computer no don't
worry about it picture of my teacher
with the globe touching the globe I no
anyway so we found a new picture of my
teacher taken at McDougle Street which
is it's a place where he taught in New
York briefly and uh it's a beautiful
photo cuz he's got his hand on top of
the
world and uh I remember
uh somebody asked a question oh I heard
yeah I was there actually and they said
um R what do all the Buddhist do when
they get
enlightened you know what I mean like
what do they do what they talk about and
then he's like well they just get
together and talk about emptiness and
stuff
anyway even though they know what each
other's going to say before they say
it
so so anyway it's a pleasure to be in a
room with so many people who spent so
many years to learn these things and I
feel like uh it's just Buddhist talking
to Buddhist but it's still something
worthwhile doing right okay so thank you
for coming it's see you tomorrow okay